Okay, Alvaro. Yay, brilliant.
So Alvaro's going to talk about how to
blow up a surface without getting
arrested.
Let me start with a real world story.
So one of the leading researchers in my
area of research was in an airport and he
was talking to a colleague through the
phone. He was like, "I tried
everything to sort out this problem, but
there's no other choice. I have to blow
up a plane". Then, the airport
security overheard him and immediately
arrested him. However, after long
hours of questioning, he was finally
released. Turns out, he had been talking
about his research. My name is Alvaro,
and I am a researcher in algebraic
geometry, which is an area of pure
mathematics that uses algebra to study
geometry. More specifically, my area of
research are surfaces. Surfaces
are basically the shells of 3D
objects that we know, such as the sphere,
the cone, or the cylinder. My job as a
mathematician is to try to see what these
things have in common, what these shapes
have in common, and what allows us to
tell them apart. So, for instance, let's
look at an easy case, the sphere and the
cone. The surface of the sphere is quite
uniform and regular and soft, whereas
the cone has this pointy bit that if
we touch it, it pinches us.
So surfaces are quite uniform and
regular, it's what we know as smooth
surfaces. Whereas surfaces that have,
you know, punchy bits and rugged
parts are what we know as singular
surfaces. And my job as a mathematician
is to determine how to transform smooth
surfaces, well, singular surfaces into
smooth surfaces. A technique that I
use to do this is what is known as a
blow-up. And this is the technique that
this researcher was talking about when he
was arrested. So the main
idea of it is, imagine that we want to
transform a cone into a sphere. One thing
that we could do is, we can imagine that
the surface of the cone is made out of
rubber, and it has a hole in the bottom,
so we can plump a bike pump, and we
can just inflate the cone until
somehow the pointy bit just starts
becoming more and more uniform until it
resembles the sphere. This is the idea
behind blow-ups, and this is the idea
behind my research. What I do is, I
use computers to study how to
make very singular surfaces, like the one
you can see on the screen, into very
smooth surfaces. And you might be
wondering, why am I interested in
something like this? Well, my research has
applications in many areas. For instance,
many objects in physics, such as black
holes, are modeled as singularities
in time and space, for instance. It also
has applications in 3D modeling, where
resolving singularities allows us to
have more accurate and more
interactive models. So either by
studying, if we want to study the corners
of the universe or make our favorite
characters look better, many of the
problems in mathematics can be solved
with a bang. Thank you.
So, literally ended his talk with a bang.
Brilliant. Okay.